Guide to the Nancy Tatnall Fuller Research Collection on Joseph Swift
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Nancy Tatnall Fuller Research Collection on Joseph Swift
1858-1997
WA MSS S-2437
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.76
(4 boxes)
Nancy Tatnall Fuller's collection on Joseph Swift was acquired during research for her book Joseph Swift in the Wild West. Over 40 letters between Joseph Swift and family members from 1858 to 1887 describe frontier life in Montana, the gold rush, cattle herding, the Civil War, settler relations with Piegan Indians, and local news. Swift omitted mention of his friendship with the Plummers and Joseph Slade in letters home though his father commented on vigilante executions in Montana. Also included are Fuller's research notes and correspondence, typescript transcripts of Swift's letters, photocopied articles and books about vigilante activity in Bannack, obituaries for Joseph Swift and Francis M. Thompson, background material for Fuller's book and a copy of Joseph Swift in the Wild West. Addition to the collection in 2004 includes financial records, receipts, correspondence and other material related to Swift's investment and participation in various companies, including the Tally-On-Top Salesbook Company, the Geometric Drill Company, and the Uncle Sam Gold Mining Company.
Fuller, Nancy Tatnall
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of John Gambell, 2002 and 2004.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
NANCY TATNALL FULLER AND JOSEPH SWIFT
In 1997 Nancy Tatnall Fuller published Joseph Swift in the Wild West, a biography of her great grandfather. The book, which described Swift's life in Montana from 1862 through 1864, was based on letters between Swift and family members that had been collected by Caroline Tatnall Welles.
Joseph Swift was born to Samuel Swift and Mary Ann Royer Swift in Norriton Township, Pennsylvania on December 16, 1843. After nine years the Swift family moved to Norristown, PA, where Joseph enrolled in a private school. Swift began working in Philadelphia as an office boy for David S. Brown & Co in 1859. Two years later Swift suffered a case of pneumonia that threatened to develop into tuberculosis. In 1862, at the age of 18, Swift set out on a journey up the Missouri River to Montana in hopes of restoring his health.
During his first year in Montana, Swift worked at the Blackfeet Indian Government Experimental Farm in Sun River. In July of 1863, he moved to the gold rush town of Bannack where he worked as a clerk for Francis M. Thompson. In Bannack, Swift and Thompson boarded with James and Martha Vail. Other boarders included Martha Vail's sister, Electa Bryan Plummer, and Electa's husband Henry Plummer, the sheriff of Bannack.
In January of 1864, Henry Plummer was captured and hanged by vigilantes who accused him of being complicit in a series of Montana robberies and murders. Vigilantes hung another of Swift's friends, Joseph Slade, in March. Following these events, the Vails left Bannack and Joseph Swift began rooming with another family, the Edgertons, until his own departure later that year.
By December 1864, Swift had returned to Pennsylvania where he was employed by the Sugar Creek Oil Company in Venango County. After a brief period he accepted a position with his brother William at Swift and Courtney (later the Diamond Match Company) and began a career in safety match manufacturing. During the years that followed, Swift married Gertrude Dorr and had six children. He retired from his position as vice-president of the Diamond Match Company in the 1880s, and moved with his family to Wilmington, Delaware. He died on July 13, 1917, at the age of 71.
Scope and Contents
The Nancy Tatnall Fuller Research Collection on Joseph Swift consists of correspondence between Joseph Swift and family members along with correspondence, transcripts, research notes, and other papers which Nancy Tatnall Fuller produced or consulted while researching Joseph Swift in the Wild West (1997). The papers have been organized into two series, Family Correspondence of Joseph Swift and Research Files of Nancy Tatnall Fuller, which span the dates 1858-1997. The collection is housed in three boxes. Box 3 contains Oversize material.
Series I, Joseph Swift Family Correspondence, is organized into three subseries: Outgoing, Incoming, and Third Party. Each subseries is arranged chronologically. Transcripts and annotated photocopies of some letters, created by Nancy Tatnall Fuller during her research, are housed in folders at the end of the first two subseries (folders 10, 20, and 21).
Topics covered in letters sent by Joseph Swift include steamboat travel, his health, mail delivery on the Montana frontier, his employment with Francis M. Thompson, settler relations with Piegan Indians, cattle herding, and the Montana gold rush. Incoming correspondence consists of letters from Swift's father and siblings which describe local news, Civil War battles, the draft, and unrest among "the Sioux in Minnesota" (folders 13, 14). Swift appears to have written a letter (not included in the collection) to his mother shortly after Henry Plummer's execution in January 1864. Samuel Swift's reply on March 16, 1864 indicates that his son's account of the execution in Bannack did not explain the connection he harbored to the dead man (folder 16). In the two existing 1864 letters Swift wrote to his family, he made no further mention of vigilante activities.
Third Party correspondence includes letters between Swift's wife, Gertrude Dorr Swift, and family members, a brief letter from Horatio Dorr to Joseph's brother William and an 1876 letter from Adeline Dorr, Gertrude's sister, to Joseph Swift's son and daughter-in-law (folder 26). The letters are primarily about family matters. Transcripts and annotated photocopies created by Nancy Tatnall Fuller are housed in folders at the end of the first two subseries (folders 10, 20 and 21).
Series II, Nancy Tatnall Fuller Research Files, is organized into four subseries: Correspondence, Printed Material, Subject Files, and Other Papers. Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent and consists predominantly of letters between Fuller and individuals or organizations she believed could supply her with material for her book.
Printed Material is arranged alphabetically by name of author. The subseries includes Fuller's book, Joseph Swift in the Wild West (1997), Bannack: Cradle of Montana (1991) by F. Lee Graves, and photocopies of articles and other works which Fuller consulted during her research. Some of the photocopies are annotated.
Subject Files contains obituaries for Francis M. Thompson and Joseph Swift along with photocopied articles and a series of Montana highway maps.
Other Papers is arranged alphabetically by type of material and includes Fuller's labelled binder dividers; manuscript and typescript notes for Joseph Swift in the Wild West; drafts of a timeline for Joseph Swift's life; and photocopies of title pages for works included in Fuller's bibliography.
Series III, Additions Since 2003, includes correspondence relating to Joseph Swift's investments as well as to the settlement of the estates of Samuel and Elizabeth Swift. A group of letters relates to Joseph Swift's investment in the Tally-on-Top Salesbook Company. The Joseph Swift Personal Papers subseries is arranged in chronological order and consists of insurance forms, a stock certificate from the Uncle Sam Gold Mining Company (Joseph Swift was secretary of the company), accounting sheets, receipts, property tax receipts, and Elizabeth Swift's account with the Pennsylvania Company for Insurance. Includes a manuscript tally of Joseph Swift's interest in the estate of Elizabeth Swift. Geometric Drill Company material includes a prospectus for the company, a contract, and company financial information.
Nancy Tatnall Research Files is organized into Printed Material and Other Papers. Printed Material includes maps, periodicals, and photocopies which Tatnall consulted while writing her book. Other Papers consists of a tracing of an overland journey by rail, steamship and foot from Philadelphia to Bannack; a photocopy of the tracing; and several photocopied images of the Swift family, with identification in ink by Tatnall.
Cattle herding -- Montana; Frontier and pioneer life -- Montana; Gold mines and mining -- Montana; Indians of North America -- Great Plains; Piegan Indians; Vigilantes -- Montana; Bannack (Mont.); Norristown (Pa.); Sun River (Mont.); United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Wilmington (Del.); Receipts (financial records) -- United States -- 19th century; Receipts (financial records) -- United States -- 20th Century; Stock certificates -- Dakota Territory; Fuller, Nancy Tatnall; Swift, Joseph, 1843-1917; Geometric Drill Company (New Haven, Conn.); Tally-On-Top Salesbook Company; Uncle Sam Gold Mining Company
- Joseph Swift Family Correspondence, 1858-1886; Series I; 0.2; (.5 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I., Joseph Swift Family Correspondence, is organized in three subseries: Outgoing, Incoming and Third Party. Material within each subseries is arranged chronologically.
  - OUTGOING
    - Correspondence, 1858 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 1866-68 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 1869 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, 1870 Aug 16 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Empty envelope, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Transcripts and annotated photocopies of correspondence (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - INCOMING
    - Correspondence, 1862 Apr-May (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, 1862 Jul (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, 1862 Oct (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence, 1862 Dec (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence, 1863 Oct (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 16-17)
    - Correspondence, 1868 Apr 26 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - ALS from Samuel Swift (son), 1886 Feb 21 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Transcripts and annotated photocopies of correspondence (Box 1, Folder 20-21)
  - THIRD PARTY
    - ALS to Gertrude Swift from Adeline Dorr, 1861 Jul 16 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - ALS to William Swift from Horatio Dorr, 1869 Mar 29 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - ALS to Eliza Swift from Gertrude Swift, 1869 Dec 17 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - ALS to Eliza Swift from Gertrude Swift, 1870 May 11 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - ALS to Samuel and Franny Swift from Adeline Dorr, 1876 Mar 31 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Nancy Tatnall Research Files, 1987-97; Series II; 0.63; (1.5 boxes)
  Series II. Nancy Tatnall Research Files, is organized into four subseries: Correspondence, Printed Material, Subject Files, and Other Papers. Material in each subseries is arranged alphabetically by name, subject or type of material.
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - Birney, Hoffman, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 27)
      Correspondence with Frances Swift Tatnall (photocopy).
      Related Archival Materials note
      See also: McEwan, W. L., box 2, folder 34
    - Cruse, William T., 1989 Sep 12 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      Includes Virginia City Gazette, v. 10, Summer 1989.
    - Dedera, Don, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Dempsey, Al, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 30)
      Includes map of Bannack (photocopy).
    - Great Falls Public Library, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      Includes description of Blackfeet Indian Governmental Farm from A Pictorial History of the Sun River Valley (photocopy).
    - Greenfield Massachusetts Public Library, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Massachusetts Historical Society, 1987-92 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - McEwan, W. L., 1996, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 34)
      Enclosing a copy of a letter between Hoffman Birney and Mrs. Lea, 1929; a letter between Martha Plassman and Hoffman Birney, 1929; and passages from Vigilantes.
    - Montana Historical Society, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - New England Historic and Genealogical Society, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Plassman, Martha Edgerton
      See: McEwan, W.L., box 2, folder 34 and Oversize, box 3, folder 66
    - Unidentified recipients, 1992 Jul 24 (Box 1, Folder 37)
      Form letter asking for copies of Joseph Swift correspondence.
  - PRINTED MATERIAL
    - Birney, Hoffman. Vigilantes, 1929 (photocopy), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 38-39)
    - Dedera, Don. "Ghost Towns with Spirit", Historic Preservation, 1989 (photocopy), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Dimsdale, Thomas J. "The Hanging of Captain Slade", Montana Margins, 1946 (photocopy), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Edgerton, Mary Wright. Passages from A Governor's Wife on the Mining Frontier, 1976 (photocopy), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 42)
      Includes copy of bibliography.
    - Frohlicher, S. V. Stone Age to Space Age in 100 Years, 1981, p. 14-15 (photocopy), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Fuller, Nancy Tatnall. Joseph Swift in the Wild West, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Graves, F. Lee. Bannack: Cradle of Montana, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Hough, Emerson. The Passing of the Frontier: a Chronicle of the Old West, 1921, p. 66-81 (photocopy), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Overholser, Joel. Pages from Fort Benton: World's Innermost Port (photocopy), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Plassman, Martha Edgerton. News articles (photocopy), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Rowe, Jean Conrad. "St. Peter's Mission" from Mountains and Meadows: a Pioneer History of Cascade, Chestnut Valley, Hardy, St. Peter's Mission and Castner Falls, [1970] (photocopy) (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Sun River Valley Historical Society. Pages from A Pictorial History of the Sun River Valley, 1989 (photocopy), 1992 Aug 18 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Thompson, Francis M. "Pioneer Experiences in Great Northwest", 1911 (photocopy), 1992 Aug 18
    - Thompson, Francis M. Reminiscences of Four-Score Years, 1912-14 (photocopy), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 51-52)
    - Towle, Virginia Rowe. "Electa Bryan Plummer: A Good Woman who Loved a Bad Man" from Vigilante Woman, 1966 (photocopy), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Vaughn, Robert. Pages from Then and Now; or, Thirty-Six Years in the Rockies, 1900 (photocopy) (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - SUBJECT FILES
    - Bannack, [1995] (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Montana, 1990-94 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Thompson, Francis M., n.d. (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Swift, Joseph, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - OTHER PAPERS
    - Binder dividers (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - Notes for Joseph Swift in the Wild West, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 60-61)
    - Timeline drafts, typescript, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Title pages for bibliography (photocopy), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 63)
- Additions Since 2003, 1882-1993; Series III; 0.42; (1 box)
  - JOSEPH SWIFT FAMILY CORRESPONDENCE
    - Correspondence, 1891-1919 (Box 4, Folder 68)
    - Correspondence with Tally-on-Top Salesbook Company, 1895 May-Jun (Box 4, Folder 69)
  - JOSEPH SWIFT PERSONAL PAPERS
    - Financial and Insurance Records
      Material arranged in chronological order.
      - Equitable Life Assurance. Tontine policy tables, 3 blank forms completed in manuscript, 1882, 1893 (Box 4, Folder 70)
      - Uncle Sam Gold Mining Company. Stock certificate for 500 shares, 1886 May 17 (Box 4, Folder 71)
      - Accounts, 1887-1894, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 72-73)
      - Receipts, 1888-1910 (Box 4, Folder 74-78)
      - Receipts, property taxes, 1893-1912 (Box 4, Folder 79)
      - Pennsylvania Company for Insurance. Elizabeth Swift account, statements, typescript on carbon, 1912-16, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 80)
      - Pennsylvania Company for Insurance. Original folder for Elizabeth Swift account, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 81)
      - "Estimate of Value of Joseph Swift's Interest in Estate of Elizabeth Swift," manuscript balance sheets, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 82)
    - Geometric Drill Co.
      - Contract with Wharton Switch Company, draft, 1893 (Box 4, Folder 83)
      - Inventory and balance sheet, 1894 Nov 1 (Box 4, Folder 84)
      - Prospectus, [189?] (Box 4, Folder 85)
  - NANCY TATNALL RESEARCH FILES
    Arranged alphabetically by folder title.
    - Printed Material
      - Bannack State Park, printed map, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 86)
      - De Lacy, W. W. Map of the Territory of Montana with Portions of the Adjoining Territories...1865, partial photocopies, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 87)
      - Montana Department of Fish, Wildlife & Parks. Bannack Free Press 1, no. 1, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 88)
      - Montana's Gold West Country Travel Guide 4, magazine, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 89)
      - Ovitt, Mabel. Map and appendix from Golden Treasure, annotated photocopies (Box 4, Folder 90)
      - Travel Montana, Department of Commerce. Montana: 1993-94 Official Highway Map, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 91)
    - Other Papers
      - Map of journey from Philadelphia to Bannack, tracing on carbon and photocopy of tracing (Box 4, Folder 92)
      - Swift family photographs, annotated photocopies, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 93)
- Oversize, 0.34; (1 box)
  Oversize contains material from Series I-II, and is arranged in box order.
  - Annotated photocopies of correspondence (in Series I) (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Virginia City Gazette, vol. 10, Summer 1989 (in Series II) (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Plassman, Martha Edgerton. News articles, 1928 (in Series II), n.d. (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Thompson, Francis M. "Pioneer Experiences in Great Northwest", 1911 (in Series II), n.d. (Box 3, Folder 67)